Sahaja yogis should not fall to such a level
Los sahaja yoguis no debebían caer hasta el nivel
I would say those who have been worrying and all that,
Aquellos que se han pasado la mañana preocupados
should go into great meditation and understand
deberían entrar en meditación y entender
that you are insulting yourself. You are saints;
que os estáis insultando a vosotros mismos. Sois santos,
why should you worry about what plane you are going to get,
¿por qué deberíais preocuparos sobre que avión vais a coger
what you are not going to get? Shows that your level is very low;
y cual no? Muestra que tenéis un nivel muy bajo
definitely; all those who have worried.
todos aquellos que os habéis preocupado tanto.
You have come here under My protection,
Habéis venido aquí bajo mi protección
and you will go back under My protection.
y volveréis bajo mi protección.
that you are all part and parcel of My being;
que quizás no tendríamos ningún Puja. Debéis saber
I have put you in My body and you have to behave yourself.
os he puesto dentro de mi cuerpo y debéis comportaros.
so in such an auspicious day when we all have come here
Así en este día tan auspicioso en el cual todos hemos venido aquí,
to do this special puja, and I would say this should be called
para celebrar este Puja especial, que debería llamarse
as a Mahalakshmi Puja because it’s something to do
Mahalaxmi Puja porque tiene relación
with the industry of this country, and of the whole world.
con la industria de este país y del mundo entero.
Unless and until all those human ventures are connected with God
Hasta que todas las empresas  no estén conectadas con Dios,
they cannot get their perfect stage and their status.
no podrán alcanzar su estado perfecto.
That’s why we have problems now in the West.
Por eso tenemos problemas en Occidente,
Supposed to be very clever people, very smart,
donde se supone que la gente es muy inteligente, muy sofisticada,
very well equipped, well educated. We are having recessions
muy bien equipada y educada. Y sin embargo tienen recesión
and things because they have no balance.
y otros problemas, porque no tienen equilibrio;
They don’t know that there is God’s power which works everything,
no saben que existe el poder de Dios  que hace todas las cosas
and when you neglect that, this is what happens to you.
y cuando se menosprecia este poder, esto es lo que os ocurre.
Now for any venture that we do of this kind,
Para cualquier trabajo que hacemos de este tipo,
first of all we have to use a lot of material from the Mother Earth,
se requiere mucha materia de la Madre Tierra;
but if it is taken for a proper purpose, for constructive things
y cuando se utiliza para un propósito adecuado, con un fin constructivo
and for helping others, with a balance,
para ayudar a otros, pero siempre con equilibrio,
then Mother Earth can think, She can produce, more and more,
entonces la Madre Tierra puede pensar y producir más y más
all this She has produced before.
de lo que anteriormente había producido.
She can produce for people who are sensible,
Ella puede producir muchas cosas para gente que es sensata,
who are in tune with God, not just making money for themselves,
que está en armonía con Dios, y  no que sólo sacan dinero para si mismos,
or for their own purpose, but are thinking in totality,
o para su propio proposito, sino para los que piensan en una totalidad,
thinking as to what we can achieve by doing this.
que piensan qué se puede lograr con todo esto
And that is how an industry can grow.
y así es como puede triunfar una industria.
Now we see in Japan so much industry has grown,
Ya habéis visto que también hay una gran industria en Japón,
but no spirituality. They are not at all happy people.
pero no hay espiritualidad, no son gente feliz.
Their children are suffering, families are suffering.
Los niños están sufriendo, las familias también.
Money cannot get the total well being of a human being.
El dinero no aporta todo el bienestar al ser humano.
So a balance has to be drawn.
Por tanto debe haber un equilibrio.
Especially in our country, thank God, we didn’t have
Gracias a Dios que en nuestro país no ha habido
such a fast industrialization, and that’s why we are saved
una industrialización tan rápida. Por eso nos hemos librado
of lots of problems that the Western people are suffering,
de muchos problemas que tienen los occidentales
about which the Indians are not aware.
y de los que los hindúes no son conscientes.
They think you are all living in a very comfortable life there.
Piensan que allí vivís una vida muy cómoda.
Industry has to go hand-in-hand with the handicrafts,
Pero la industria tiene que ir mano a mano con la artesanía.
and the industrialists have to also look after the artists,
Y los  industriales tienen que apoyar a los artistas,
because otherwise who will look after them?
porque si no ¿Quién cuidará de ellos?
How will they bring forth the balance between the art and the industry?
¿Cómo traerán equilibrio entre el arte y la industria?
And art is such a soothing thing for these hard-working people.
El arte es algo que alivia a las personas que trabajan mucho,
They work the whole day, then there is some sort of a music,
al terminar el trabajo del día, escuchan música,
art, to console them, to give them peace, to relax them,
el arte de la música, que les reconforta, les da paz, les relaja
and a balance. So I would say that all industries
y les da equilibrio. Por eso la industria
must take to some artistic ventures also, or they should also produce things.
debería hacer algún trabajo artístico también.
After I was telling Rajesh many a times that you should try to produce
Le he dicho a Rajesh que aquí deberían intentar crear
something artistic out of the steel scrap that is left over, will be a good idea.
algo de artesanía con los restos de acero que sobran.
They have tried something like that.
Ellos han intentado hacer algo de este tipo.
But industry should not be looked down upon
Pero la industria tampoco debe ser mal vista,
as it is looked down upon in our country.
como ahora en nuestro país,
I mean, as if industrialists are the greatest thieves
donde los industriales parecen los peores ladrones,
and all the politicians are saints in this country. It’s the other way around I think.
y los políticos los santos. Aunque Yo creo que es al revés.
It should be treated with respect,
La industria debe ser tratada con respeto
and should be understood that it’s very important.
y deberíamos entender que es muy importante.
And the industrialists, if they become also enlightened,
Y los industriales deben ser gente iluminada,
they can do a lot, not only to their own country,
así pueden hacer mucho bien, no sólo a su país,
but also to the people whom they are looking after.
sino a la gente que está a su cargo.
So in the Mahalakshmi principle,
Por tanto, en el principio de Mahalaxmi,
Mahalakshmi has various mudras.
Mahalaxmi muestra varios mudras.
One of the mudra is that She puts Her right hand like this.
Uno es levantando la mano derecha
Now this right hand is to give protection to people
que significa que da protección a la gente
who are under the protection, or under the service,
que está bajo la protección o al servicio
of some rich man, or the industrialist we can call it.
de un hombre rico, o de un hombre de industria.
In India if you call somebody a rich man it’s like abusing him.
En India si decís un hombre rico, es como un insulto,
Nobody likes it, because the rich are always shown
a nadie le gusta. Porque los hombres ricos siempre han tenido fama
to be the worst people, which is not so.
de ser los peores; pero en mi experiencia esto no es así,
In My own experience it’s not so. If there’s a poor man also he could be terrible.
porque hemos visto que un hombre pobre puede ser terrible.
We have had very bad experiences now, in Ganapatipule,
Hemos tenido muy malas experiencia en Ganapatipule
of very poor people how they behaved
con gente muy pobre, que se han comportado
in a very funny manner - supposed to be poor.
muy mal y con muy malos modales.
So it should be a proper balance, it should be brought to a proper balance,
Por tanto debe haber un equilibrio adecuado
between the understanding of the poor and the rich, and the rich and the poor.
en el entendimiento entre ricos y pobres, entre pobres y ricos.
After some time you will find that people will not consider poverty
Después de un tiempo veréis que la gente no considerará a la pobreza
or riches as so important, but the richness of the spirit
o a la riqueza  tan importantes, sino que la riqueza del espíritu
will become very important.
pasará a ser lo importante.
That is what is going to be the Sahaj nations
Así serán las naciones Sahaja,
where the richness of the heart, the spirituality,
donde la riqueza del corazón, la espiritualidad,
oneness with the Divine, will become the greatest boon
la unión con el Divino, se convertirá en la bendición mas grande
for everyone. But still we are struggling
de todo el mundo. Pero todavía estamos luchando
to be on that state; many are; and still we go into materialistic tantrums
por llegar a ese estado y aún caemos cosas materialistas
or some sort of a stupid worrying fall.
y en preocupaciones estúpidas.
All these must be carefully watched.
Todo esto lo debéis observar cuidadosamente.
If you can keep this chariot of new progress
Si mantenéis este carro del nuevo progreso,
progressing faster
progresando cada vez mas rápido,
we are going to create a new world of complete harmony,
entonces crearemos un mundo de completa armonía,
complete peace, joy and love. But for that
completa paz y amor. Pero para ello,
you are the ones who have to do it. I cannot do it.
sois vosotros los que debéis hacerlo, Yo no puedo hacerlo.
If I could have done it
Si Yo hubiera podido hacerlo
I would not have asked you to join Sahaja Yoga.
no os habría pedido que vinierais a Sahaja Yoga.
It’s like the horses and the charioteer;
Es como los caballos de un carro y el jinete.
horses are to be driven; charioteer doesn’t drive the chariot.
Los caballos han de ser conducidos, el jinete no lleva el carro.
In the same way you must understand your responsibility
De la misma manera debéis comprender vuestra responsabilidad,
that this is the greatest work we are doing.
estamos haciendo el trabajo más grande.
It’s not only the industry, or the labor and the capital,
No es solo la Industria, o el obrero, o el capital,
I’m talking about, but I’m talking about the totality of well being.
sino que estoy hablando de la totalidad del bienestar.
Of course all of this is a part and parcel of that, no doubt.
Sin duda que todo esto forma una parte de ello.
But the balance should be with the totality.
Pero el equilibrio debe estar con la totalidad.
So we have to think of a total well being.
Debéis pensar en el bienestar del todo.
Once we start thinking of the total well being then –
Una vez que pensáis en esta totalidad,
first thing that should come to us:
entonces lo primero que debería venirnos a la mente es:
Are we capable of bringing up that total well being? Are we?
¿Somos capaces de instaurar o crear este bienestar total? ¿Lo somos?
Have we got the total well being within ourselves or not? Have we?
¿Tenemos ese bienestar total en nuestro interior o no? ¿Lo tenemos?
We are still worried if the plane is coming or not,
Pero todavía estamos preocupados de si llega o no el avión,
I mean, we are so mundane, so little, so small.
o si lo cogemos. ¡Somos tan mundanos!, ¡tan pequeños!
With one bandhan you can control any plane, any atmosphere,
Con un bandhan podéis controlar cualquier avión, cualquier atmósfera,
and here you are, I mean, still worried about things
y todavía estáis aquí preocupados por cosas
which are absolutely under your control.
que están realmente bajo vuestro control.
So this totality has to be thought over.
Por tanto, debéis pensar en esta totalidad.
What is this totality that Mother is talking about?
¿Qué es esta totalidad de la que Madre habla?
In this totality a world has to be created of people,
En esta totalidad hay que crear un mundo de personas diferentes
by the people, who have no fear. This fear has to be given up.
por gente que no tenga miedo. Este miedo tiene que desaparecer.
Behind all this nonsensical nervousness is fear.
Detrás de todo este tonto nerviosismo que tenéis, hay miedo.
So for that, what She does is to give  Avaida
Para ello la Diosa os da protección,
Under Her protection you are beyond fear, you are protected.
bajo su protección estáis mas allá de cualquier temor;
But if you do not want to believe in yourself,
pero si no queréis creer en vosotros mismos,
and you don’t believe into Her protection, then no body can help you,
ni en su Protección, entonces nadie puede ayudaros,
because everything is mythical for you.
porque todo es mítico para vosotros.
In every venture that we take up we should not have any fear
En cualquier cosa que emprendáis no debéis tener ningún temor,
because God is with you. Is a fact, is the truth. You just try.
porque Dios está con vosotros, es un hecho. Probadlo.
But when you try through your ego you fall into the trap of fear.
Pero cuando lo hacéis desde vuestro ego, caéis en el miedo.
I have seen egoistical people are the most frightened people,
He visto que la gente egoísta es la gente más temerosa,
and panicked, because they panic others
y la razón es que ellos atemorizan a los demás
and so they think they can be panicked one day.
y piensan que a ellos les pueden hacer lo mismo cualquier día.
When the English were here, first of all, in India,
Cuando los ingleses estaban aquí, en los comienzos,
we were all frightened of them. Now I see
todo el mundo temía a los ingleses. Pero ahora
that in England every English family is frightened of others.
en Inglaterra todas las familias tienen miedo de los demás.
They’ll only open a chink of the door to see who is there,
Abren la puerta con una cadena puesta,
and shut it. They’re so frightened. I’m surprised,
llenos de temor. Estoy sorprendida
they are the same English who ruled us here.
de que estos sean los ingleses que una vez nos gobernaron
And we were so bewitched before them and now
y a los que nosotros mostrábamos nuestro desagrado; ahora
they are the ones who are frightened of us;
ellos nos tienen miedo a nosotros.
because when a person who is egoistical tries to dominate others
Porque cuando una persona egoísta intenta dominar a los demás,
he sees himself in the mirror and thinks
esta misma persona está en el espejo y piensa
that the other person will dominate him.
que son los otros los que le quieren dominar,
That’s how this fear creeps in, into our minds,
así es como este miedo empieza a penetrar en la mente
and we start getting all kinds of these stupid tantrums
y a raíz de ello generamos esta absurda inseguridad
out of this mythical fear.
que proviene de este falso temor.
The fear is created by our ego.
El miedo es creado únicamente por nuestro ego.
A person who has no ego, he’ll have no fear
Una persona que no tiene ego no tiene miedo,
because he has not harmed anyone.
porque si no ha hecho mal a nadie
Why should he have any fear? And such a man, or such a woman,
¿por qué habría de tener miedo?, y una persona así
will be looked after by God, because God takes over.
será totalmente cuidada por Dios, porque Dios se hace cargo,
When you surrender your ego to God He takes over.
cuando rendís vuestro ego a Dios, Él asume todo.
But those who have ego He says, “All right, go ahead,
Pero con aquellos que tienen ego, Él dice: "Adelante,
use your ego, try to protect yourself, cut your throat.”
protégete a ti mismo con el ego y córtate el cuello".
That’s what it is. So when I talk of total benevolence
Así que cuando hablo de la total Benevolencia,
I’m talking about your own total benevolence.
hablo de vuestro propia total Benevolencia;
So first is the fear,
y lo primero es el miedo,
which should go out of your mind completely
que debería salir completamente de vuestra mente
if you believe in the Almighty God. We’ll say,
si creéis en Dios todopoderoso. Decimos
“You are Almighty God, you are almighty this thing”
"¡Oh! es Dios todopoderoso, todopoderoso"
It's all lip-service. If you believe that God is almighty,
pero lo decimos superficialmente. Si creéis que Dios es todopoderoso
and you are connected with God,
y estáis conectados con Dios,
then why should you have any fear of anything?
entonces ¿por qué habríais de tener miedo?
But when we say, “Don’t have fear,” another extreme comes up,
Pero cuando decimos "No tengáis miedo" viene el otro extremo
“We don’t have fear, we can do what we like,
y pensamos que podemos hacer lo que queramos,
we can perform everything ourselves, we need not tell anyone.”
que podemos hacer lo que sea sin decírselo a nadie.
You have to tell God whatever you are doing.
Pero a Dios sí le tenéis que decir todo lo que estáis haciendo,
You have to take permission, you have to inform in His darbar,
debéis pedir su permiso, informar en su darbar,
in His court, that, “Sir, we are thinking of doing such and such thing.”
en su corte, de que pensáis hacer tal y tal cosa.
But you think you are God. You are not.
Pero pensáis que vosotros mismos sois Dios; no lo sois,
And that’s why the another part of non-fear
por eso esta otra parte de la cuestión, el "no tener miedo"
is this kind of an arbitrary behavior
crea un tipo de actitud muy arbitraria
which is very dangerous for Sahaja Yoga,
que es muy peligrosa para Sahaja Yoga,
for yourself, and for everybody else.
para vosotros mismos y para todos los demás.
The second fear, I mean, I have, is that if I tell you anything,
El segundo temor que tengo es que cuando os digo algo,
ninety-nine percent of you understand is for your benevolence,
el noventa y nueve por cien entendéis que es por vuestro bien,
is for your good. But there is one percent of people
pero hay un uno por ciento de personas
who can just react because they have too much ego and they won’t take it,
que reaccionará porque tiene mucho ego y
because they don’t think of their own benevolence.
porque no dan importancia a aquello que es bueno para ellos.
They don’t understand that if I am telling them anything,
No entienden que si les digo algo
it is just to give them completeness, totality.
es precisamente para darles a ellos mismos plenitud, totalidad.
But, on the contrary, they take a very wrong attitude;
Por el contrario adoptan una actitud muy errónea,
this is another nonsensity. So now one has to develop
lo cual es otra tontería. Uno tiene que desarrollar
a kind of a indifference to this kind of people
una cierta indiferencia hacia estas personas
who unnecessarily go to the other limit of their own destruction,
que, innecesariamente, se van al extremo de su propia destrucción
and don’t want to see what is the point in everything
y que no quieren ver cual es la esencia de todo
that I am telling you. Only I can tell you. Who else?
lo que Yo estoy diciendo. Sólo Yo puedo decíroslo, ¿quién si no?
I have to tell you what’s wrong with you,
He de deciros lo que esta equivocado en vosotros,
what you have done wrong, and then you must change it.
lo que habéis hecho mal y vosotros tenéis que cambiar.
This is another style of reaction one gets,
Este es pues otro tipo de reacción,
means they are not interested in their own benevolence,
y muestra que no están interesados en su propia benevolencia,
they’re not interested in the benevolence of their children,
ni en el bien de sus hijos,
they’re not interested in the benevolence of their country or the whole world.
ni el de su país, ni el del mundo entero.
Now why have you come to Sahaja Yoga? Just ask one question.
Entonces preguntaros ¿por qué estáis en Sahaja Yoga?
Of course for you to ascend. But ascend for what?
Desde luego que para ascender, pero ascender ¿para qué?
Supposing we bring one tube light.
Supongamos que me traen una bombilla,
For what we have to take the tube light? But for what?
¿para que nos sirve la bombilla? ¿para que?
We have to put the light. But this tube light doesn’t give light,
Para dar luz, pero si no da luz,
nothing of the kind, so what’s the use of having this tube light?
ni nada parecido,¿para qué sirve tener esta bombilla?
In the same way, what’s the use of coming to Sahaja Yoga
De la misma manera ¿de qué sirve que vengáis a Sahaja Yoga
if you cannot become the light of the Divine?
si no podéis convertiros en  la luz del Divino?
So all of you, each one of you, is not at all a small person;
Así que, todos y cada uno de vosotros, no sois una pequeña persona,
no one; but you don’t realize what you are;
lo que ocurre es que no os dais cuenta de lo que sois.
still have those funny conditionings by which you think
Todavía tenéis esos condicionamientos que os hacen pensar
you are no good. All of you can come up,
que no sois buenos. Pero todos podéis ascender
and see so many people. If they take to total benevolence
y atender a muchas personas. Si desarrolláis esa total benevolencia
within themselves it will manifest itself outside; absolutely; it’s a fact.
en vuestro interior, esto se manifestará en el exterior, es un hecho.
Then the attention is very important.
La atención es muy importante.
The attention should be on your own perfection
La atención debería estar en vuestra auto-perfección
and on your total benevolence. This is also another point people miss,
y en vuestra total benevolencia. Esto es algo que mucha gente no capta
that they start finding faults with others
y se dedica así a ver defectos en los demás
instead of finding faults with themselves.
en vez de descubrir los defectos en sí mismos.
As a result, if you look at others, what will you get out of it?
Si buscáis los defectos en los demás ¿Qué obtenéis de ello?
I just don’t understand. If somebody is wrong,
No lo entiendo. Si alguien está haciendo algo mal,
he’s doing something evil, he's bad, even if you put attention to him,
o es negativo; incluso si ponéis la atención en esa persona
what will you do about it? But if you have something wrong,
¿qué hacéis al respecto? Sin embargo, si vosotros tenéis algo mal,
you have every right, you have every control,
tenéis todo el derecho, tenéis todo el control
and you can correct yourself. This is especially Indian quality,
y podéis corregiros. Esta es la especialidad de los hindúes:
is to find faults with others.
que se dedican a ver los defectos de los demás,
They’ll never see that what’s wrong with us.
pero nunca se dicen ¿qué hay de malo en nosotros?
All the time the attention is involved in finding with faults with others.
La atención siempre está ocupada en ver los defectos de los demás,
Then how can we improve? On the contrary,
entonces ¿cómo podemos mejorar? Por el contrario,
if you start seeing faults, you get faulty much more.
si os dedicáis a ver los defectos, vosotros mismos los adquirís.
It’s a copycat nature of human beings.
La tendencia a "copiar" está en la naturaleza humana.
They see somebody doing like this,
Alguien ve a otro haciendo algo malo y me dice:
“Oh Mother, he’s a Sahaja yogi, he does like this,
"Madre es un sahaja yogui y está haciendo esto y aquello,
so what’s the harm if I do?”
así que, ¿Qué hay de malo si yo lo hago?";
But who says he’s a Sahaja yogi?
pero ¿quién ha dicho que es un sahaja yogui?
So ‘Sahaja yogi’ is not a brand, it's not a certificate,
El ser sahaja yogui no es ningún certificado, ni una marca,
it’s not a kind of a organization, but it is your own status
ni una organización; es un estado
that you have achieved. Anybody can say,
que vosotros habéis alcanzado. Cualquiera puede decir
“I’m a Sahaja Yogi.” After all I cannot stop him from saying.
que es un sahaja yogui. Yo no puedo evitar que lo diga.
I’m not such a ...(unclear). Even I have seen some mad people,
Incluso he visto a algunas personas locas,
they are Sahaja yogis, for years together they’re mad,
que son sahaja yoguis, y están locos durante años,
but they’re Sahaja yogis. But you have to see for yourself,
pero dicen que son sahaja yoguis. Pero vosotros mismos tenéis que ver
am I a Sahaja yogi or not? Before certifying yourself,
si sois o no un sahaja yogui, antes de certificaros a vosotros mismos
why don’t you find out? But despite that, I must say,
comprobad si lo sois o no. Pero, a pesar de todo,
it's such a satisfaction. I never expected that so many people
para Mí es una gran satisfacción. Nunca imaginé que tantas personas
will get their realization to begin with, never.
recibirían su realización, nunca,
I mean, I knew that it was en masse modus operandi I have developed,
sabía que era un proceso en masa lo que había desarrollado,
but I never expected. But it has happened,
pero no esperaba tal resultado. Sin embargo ha ocurrido
and even now I have to expect that all of you
y ahora espero que todos vosotros
will achieve the highest, highest positions, the paramapada (Sanskrit word),
alcancéis la posición mas alta, llamada “Paramapada”
as I said, like the North Pole, or like the Meru; absolutely atala (Indian word)
como el Polo Norte o como Meru absolutamente "Athala",
‘which cannot be disturbed’. So that’s My hope,
imperturbable. Esta es mi esperanza
and I’m sure you will all comply with it.
y estoy segura de que todos vosotros la cumpliréis.
(Talk continues in Marathi then returns to English)
(Charla en Marathi, luego vuelve a inglés)
I’ll tell you in English. I have told you many a times
Os contaré ahora en inglés la historia que ya os he contado antes
about Namadeva and Gorakumbhar, how Gorakumbhar,
de Namadeva y Gorakumar. Cuando Gorakumar
when he saw Namadeva, Namadeva saw Gorakumbhar
vio que Namadeva, Namadeva vio que Gorakumar
was kneading the clay for his pottery,
estaba amasando arcilla para su cerámica;
he just went and stood before him stunned.
se presentó y se quedo ante Él atónito
And what he says that, “I have come to see here the formless”
y le dijo: "Vine aquí para ver a Dios sin forma,
(that’s the vibrations). “But the Formless is in a form”
las vibraciones y me encuentro que Dios ha tomado forma".
This is the appreciation one should have,
Este es el gran aprecio que deberíamos tener,
one Sahaja yogi should have for another.
que un sahaja yogui debe tener por otro.
Every Sahaja yogi is a gem.
Cada sahaja yogui es una gema.
Even the thought of a gem should bring joy to you.
Incluso solo el pensamiento de la gema os debería traer gozo.
In every life, every style, in every areas, every dimensions,
En cualquier vida, en cualquier área o lugar, o estilo,
one should have this kind of a feeling. Muslims, Hindus, Christians,
uno debería tener este sentimiento. Musulmanes, Hindis, Cristianos,
we do not accept. For us we are all Sahaja yogis,
no aceptamos ninguno. Para nosotros todos somos sahaja yoguis
and we have faith in all the religions, not some above.
y tenemos fe en todas las religiones y ninguna por encima de otra.
We have faith in every thing. As well as we worship Rama
Tenemos fe en todo. Adoramos igual a Rama
we worship Muhammad Sahib also, same way, no less.
que a Mahoma, igual  en todos los sentidos.
As we worship Brahmadeva, or as we worship,
Igual que adoramos a  Brahmadeva, o igual que adoramos
we say, Dattatreya, we worship Zoroaster, there’s no difference at all,
a Adi Guru Datattreya, adoramos a Zoroastro, sin diferencia alguna,
same way. There’s a big difference in having just a same,
del mismo modo. No es que a todos les consideremos igual,
what you call, the same respect; it’s not that;
o que les tengamos el mismo respeto, no es eso,
but we worship the same way, so there’s no question
sino que les adoramos del mismo modo. Por tanto
of differentiating each other; nor on country-wise, nothing.
no hay diferenciaciones, tampoco con las nacionalidades.
And whatever defects we have, we see to it
Y cualquier defecto que tenemos vemos
that this has come from our country;
que viene de nuestro país.
which I see many Sahaja yogis tell Me, “This is typical English,
Los mismos sahaja yoguis me dicen "esto es típicamente inglés",
this is typically French, this is typically Italian.”
"esto es típicamente francés, o italiano".
They themselves tell Me. But main thing one has to understand is this,
Pero la cosa más importante que debemos entender es
that in Sahaja Yoga we have lost all these boundaries; nothing is there.
que en Sahaja Yoga hemos perdido todas estas limitaciones.
We have reached that state where we are all one.
Hemos alcanzado el estado en el que todos somos "Uno".
And the idea of any Sahaja yogi whatsoever,
Y la sola idea de cualquier sahaja yogui,
and any individual Sahaja yogi, or a group of Sahaja yogis,
de un sahaja yogui individual o un grupo de sahaja yoguis,
should fill you up with joy and a kind of a wave of joy
os debería llenar de gozo, deberíais sentir el gozo como una ola
which is continuously coming, because they are in the form of joy,
que viene constantemente. Porque estáis bajo la forma de gozo,
peace. If this appreciation is reached, then only one can say
de paz. Solo si habéis logrado este tipo de aprecio por los demás
that you are Sahaja yogis, and that is one of the tests I have seen.
podéis decir que sois sahaja yoguis. Y ésta es una de las pruebas
You love Me very much I know, all of you,
que debéis pasar. A Mí me amáis mucho, lo sé,
but unless and until you love each other how am I going to be happy?
pero hasta que no os améis entre vosotros ¿cómo vais a ser felices?
So today specially, this Mahalakshmi principle,
Así que hoy es un día especial porque el principio de Mahalaxmi
when it is awakened within you, then you get out of a Lakshmi principle,
despierta dentro de vosotros y así salís del Principio de Laxmi,
which makes you a little selfish maybe, self-centered,
que quizás os hace un poco egoístas e individualistas;
and you get into a new dimension of searching,
ahora entráis en una nueva dimensión de búsqueda,
of searching the higher value system, something beyond,
de un sistema de valores superior; algo que está más allá,
without any limitations. And that Mahalakshmi principle
sin limitaciones. Y este Principio de Mahalaxmi,
is really nothing, in essence, if you see, is nothing but you are seeking the universal love,
no es otra cosa que vuestra búsqueda del Amor Universal.
in the essence it is that. We don’t love people
En su esencia es esto. Normalmente no amamos a ciertas personas
because they belong to some country, because they look like this,
porque son de tal país, o por su apariencia,
that this is this; nothing; we love them
todo esto ya no existe para nosotros. Amamos a los demás
only because they are our part and parcel, we are one with them.
porque somos parte del Todo y parte de ellos; somos Uno con ellos.
So those who are today worshipping Mahalakshmi should feel
Así que, los que hoy estáis adorando a Mahalaxmi debéis ver
how many worshippers of Mahalakshmi are there,
cuántas personas están adorando a Mahalaxmi;
and they are all our own. It’s such a great feeling.
todos ellos son  parte de nosotros, ¡es un sentimiento tan grande!
Otherwise, in Maharashtra especially, I must say, it was horrible,
Si no, como ocurre especialmente en Maharashtra, es horrible,
one Sahaja yogi goes to preach in another Sahaj, another district.
un sahaja yogui va a hablar de Sahaja Yoga a otro distrito
(Background noise) The district leader starts fighting, just like this sound,
y el líder de ese distrito empieza a pelearse con él diciéndole
“Who are you to come here? I’m the leader”
"¿A qué has venido tu aquí? Yo soy el líder de este lugar".
Instead of respecting him, and making him a welcome guest,
En lugar de respetarle, de darle la bienvenida como invitado,
asking him what can you help, there’s a big fight.
preguntándole en que le podría ayudar; se pelean bruscamente.
It’s really surprising. How can it happen?
Es sorprendente. ¿Cómo puede suceder esto?
When Namadeva went to Punjab, Guru Nanak Sahib respected him;
Cuando Namadeva fue al Punjab, Guru Nanak le respetó mucho
not only that, but he told him that,
y no sólo eso, sino que le pidió
“You write now in Punjabi language also.”
que escribiera también en punjabi.
I have seen such a big book written by Namadeva. Can you imagine?
He visto un gran libro escrito en punjabi por Namadeva,
He included all the great saints of Maharashtra in his Granth Sahib,
incluyó todos los grandes santos de Maharashtra, en el Granth Sahib
because he knew that these are realized souls, they are higher souls.
porque Él sabía que eran almas realizadas, almas superiores.
But these Sikhs are only reading it; nothing goes into their heads.
Los sikhs lo leen pero no queda nada en sus cabezas.
What can you do? So at that time,
¿Qué se puede hacer? Así que, si en aquellos tiempos
if these saints could love each other,
los santos podían quererse entre ellos,
could express themselves in such a manner, why not we,
y podían expresarse de esa manera, ¿por qué no nosotros,
the Sahaja yogis from all over the world?
los sahaja yoguis del mundo entero?
So I would say now, that, let us see, it’s a very nice program of Ras
Ahora tendremos el baile de Raas,
(Indian word) we’ll be having, where all the Indian and foreign Sahaja yogis are going to be together,
donde los sahaja yoguis de fuera y de India estarán juntos
and are going to dance together. All such things are there.
bailarán todos juntos.
So don’t sit in groups, but mix up with others, know them,
Así que no os sentéis en grupos, mezclaros con los demás, conocerles.
and this is what we are going to know;
Así es como vamos a conocer
each and every Sahaja yogi of the whole world.
a todos los sahaja yoguis del mundo entero.
Is very important for Me that you should love each other.
Para Mí es muy importante que os améis entre vosotros.
It will really soothe Me the most, it will give Me the greatest joy,
Esto será lo que mayor alivio me dé, lo que mayor gozo me dará;
the greatest achievement, and the fulfillment of My life.
será para Mí el mayor logro y  el sentido de mi vida.
If somebody is really, definitely wrong, you just write to Me
Si alguien está verdaderamente mal escribidme y decídmelo;
and I will know, because immediately I’ll know from vibrations.
Yo lo sabré inmediatamente por las vibraciones.
Nobody can befool Me, that’s one thing for sure.
Nadie puede engañarme; os lo aseguro.
Some people say that, “Somebody has told this to Mother.
Alguien dice a veces "Tal persona le ha dicho esto a Madre",
” Nothing can be told to Mother, you don’t know;
pero nada se le puede decir a Madre,
I am too cunning for all this. Nobody can tell Me anything;
soy demasiado "astuta" para todo esto. Nadie puede decirme nada,
I know each and every... I play around a little bit,
Conozco todos y cada uno. Yo juego un poco aquí y allá,
but I know each and every person. I give them a chance
pero conozco a cada uno de vosotros. Os doy una oportunidad
to hang themselves for a time being.
durante un tiempo,
But never believe that anybody can befool Me, and tell anything.
pero no penséis que alguien puede engañarme diciéndome algo.
I listen to everyone, and you can try that.
Yo escucho a todo el mundo, ¿podéis hacerlo vosotros también?
If you love another Sahaja yogi,
Si amáis a otro sahaja yogui,
this loving process itself is so joy giving.
el mismo proceso de este amor da mucho gozo.
When you first saw Me this time on the stage, you felt that way,
Cuando me visteis por primera vez en el escenario, os sentisteis así
because this process of loving is the greatest joy-giving thing.
porque este proceso de amor es lo que mayor gozo da.
So be happy, be joyous. If some people are missing the plane,
Así que sed felices, si algunas personas pierden el avión
well and good, you will live with other Sahaja yogis,
no pasa nada, se pueden quedar aquí con otros sahaja yoguis;
you are after all, you are somewhere in the world, you are not lost.
después de todo estáis en un "lugar del mundo"; no estáis perdidos.
Even if you are in the sea, you are there, on the plane you are there.
Incluso si "estáis" en el mar, estáis allí, en el avión, estáis allí,
What does it matter? Why is it so important
¿qué importa?, ¿por qué es tan importante
that this plane must be reserved, and you must worry about this plane,
tener la reserva de este avión, y preocuparos tanto por el avión,
“I must get out at this time” There’s no need.
por salir a esta hora.? No hay necesidad de esta preocupación.
Wherever you are you are with Sahaja yogis,
Dondequiera que estéis, estáis con sahaja yoguis,
so why worry?
entonces ¿por qué preocuparse?
You are, that’s the point. Like many people ask Me,
La cuestión es que vosotros "SOIS". Mucha gente me pregunta,
“Mother You travel so much, how is it You don’t get tired?”
"Madre viajas tanto, ¿cómo es que no estás cansada?"
Because I never think I am travelling, I just think, “I am,”
Pero Yo no pienso que viajo, sólo pienso que "YO SOY",
that’s all. Whether in the plane or here, or there,
eso es todo, tanto si estoy en el avión, como aquí o allí,
I am just there. I have to tell Me I am traveling,
simplemente SOY. Tengo que decirme a Mí misma que estoy viajando.
then again I forget. So you are,
Y de nuevo se me olvida. Así que vosotros SOIS,
whether you are here or in England, or anywhere,
tanto si estáis aquí, como en Inglaterra, o en cualquier parte.
or you are here or you are there. So why to worry?
ESTÁIS aquí, SOIS. ¿Por qué preocuparse?
Specially with the plane - I think there is something wrong
Especialmente con los aviones, creo que los occidentales tienen
with the Western genetics - the plane enters into their Kundalini,
un problema genético. Creo que el avión entra en sus Kundalinis
I think, and they go so bizarre with the airplanes.
y se desesperan de una manera increíble; esto de los aviones
Something I’ve never been able to understand it.
es algo que nunca he podido entender.
I’ve given them so many lessons to show that don’t do all this nonsense,
Les he dado tantas lecciones acerca de esto,
but still they go on doing like this.
pero todavía continúan comportándose de la misma manera.
But if I tell them they feel guilty,but again they do it.
Si les digo esto se sienten culpables, pero luego lo repetirán.
Next time if your plane is eight o’clock,
La próxima vez, si vuestro avión es a las 8 a.m.,
go at nine o’clock, the plane will wait for you till ten o’clock,
id al aeropuerto a las 9 a.m. El avión os esperará hasta las 10.
take it from Me. It has happened; so many can tell this.
Os lo aseguro. Esto ya ha ocurrido, muchos pueden contar esto.
So many experiences are there. I mean, we haven’t written them down,
Hay muchas experiencias que no hemos escrito;
but people know how planes have been delayed for us.
pero la gente sabe como los aviones se han retrasado sólo por nosotros.
I have never missed a plane all My life, and when I missed it,
Yo nunca he perdido un avión y si esto ha ocurrido
it was with a purpose; these big things happened.
ha sido con un propósito y algo grande había detrás de ello.
So it is important, it’s a drama.
Es importante saber que es una obra de teatro.
The worry should be one:
Sólo deberíamos tener una preocupación y es:
“Why can’t I love everyone as I love myself?”
"¿Por qué no puedo amar a los demás como me amo a mi mismo?"
I tell you only this universal love will give you
Os aseguro que es sólo este Amor Universal el que os puede dar
that confidence and that higher status.
confianza y ese estado superior.
Why these saints suffered for you?
¿Por qué aquellos santos sufrieron por vosotros?
Why did Christ suffer for you?
¿Por qué Cristo sufrió por vosotros?
Why Muhammad Sahib suffered for you?
¿Por qué Mahoma sufrió por vosotros?
Why anybody talked to you about Dharma?
¿Por qué hablaron del Dharma?
Why Gnaneshwara wrote Gnaneshwari? Why?
¿Por qué Ganeshwara escribió Ganeshwari? ¿Por qué?
What did they get?
¿Qué obtuvieron de ello?
This satisfaction of their expression of universal love.
La satisfacción de haber expresado su Amor Universal.
All the great poets, William Blake or anyone,
Todo lo que han hecho los grandes poetas, como William Blake
whatever they have done, it’s just
cualquier cosa que han hecho, lo han hecho
because they have this universal love and they want to express it.
porque tenían este amor universal y querían expresarlo.
Why not you do it?
¿Por qué no hacéis esto vosotros?
So if you want your Mahalakshmi principle
Si queréis mantener la llama del Principio de Mahalaxmi
to be all the time burning, then please
encendida, entonces por favor,
see that you love each and every Sahaja yogi.
aseguraos de que amáis a todos los sahaja yoguis.
That’s the message today. I hope you’ll understand that.
Este es el mensaje de hoy y espero que lo entendáis.